Can you explain how lifestyle factors
like diet, exercise, and sleep influence
hormone levels? What changes would you
recommend for optimal hormonal
health? When a man is slightly older and
he's suboptimal or and and
symptomatic, I I do recommend the
lifestyle changes and I will go over
some of them and I do recommend them for
every living person regardless because
you just, you know, it's just good to do
good things for your body. But to think
that that's going to optimize your
hormones is probably a long shot. Um, I
would say properly administered hormone
replacement is the answer. Now, if
you're young and you are suffering from
suboptimal hormones, more often than
not, it is self-induced based on
lifestyle choices. Uh, and those people
will see marginally better results when
they change their lifestyle. You know,
guys my age, your age, I think we're the
same age actually. Um, you know, at at
this point in our life, we we need to be
on replacement therapy. It's not, you
know, eating better and sleeping more is
not going to optimize us. If we get a 10
or 20% bump in our natural production,
it's still deficient for where we want
to feel. But if you're 22 years old and
you're not happy with your hormone
profile, reassess what you're doing. I'm
going to give you the scientific
answers. And if you think that they're
unattainable, then do the best you can.
I know people are going to say, "Well,
that's not realistic." I get it. I'm
going to tell you what science wants
your body to do and then you meet it
halfway or 3/4 or wherever you want.
Zero alcohol. Absolutely zero. Never
ever ever ever have an alcoholic
beverage for the rest of your life. That
is the scientific answer first and
foremost because it is one of the most
toxic things on the planet. And I know a
lot of people are going to be like,
"Well, no. I I I can't do that." Okay,
fine. I gave you the answer. You don't
have to listen. So, just have less
drinks or just don't drink as often. But
zero alcohol is going to be your best
friend. Sleep. Get eight or nine hours
of sleep every single night
uninterrupted. Again, people are going
to say, "I can't. I got to be up for
work." I get it. I'm telling you what
the answer is. Do the best you can. If
you're sleeping 4 hours, try for six. Go
to bed an hour earlier. You know what I
mean? Don't play with your phone. Don't
watch TV before bed so you get deeper
REM sleep. you know, maybe read a book
and and and put on some some low light
so that you're not interrupting your
your sleep pattern.
Caffeine, I know everyone's going to
say, "Oh, it's an antioxidant. Caffeine
is a good stimulant. It enhances brain
activity." Yes, but caffeine also
greatly disrupts sleep. The halflife is
longer than you realize. If you have a
cup of coffee midday, it's going to
interrupt your sleep at night. So,
cutting out caffeine altogether, and
again, I understand it's not realistic.
Hey, I'm drinking a protein coffee with
caffeine right now. I usually have
coffee in the morning. I'm not perfect,
but I am telling you what scientifically
your body requires to be optimal. Okay?
So, optimization comes from doing things
correctly. Avoid alcohol. Sleep better.
Avoid caffeine. Avoid stimulants. Avoid
sugar. Sugar is terrible for everything.
Now, notice I didn't say avoid
carbohydrates. I said avoid sugar. Okay?
You can eat vegetables. They contain
carbohydrates. You can eat starches like
potatoes. They contain carbohydrates.
But ensure that you eat your carbs with
proteins and fiber to lower the glycemic
index and the insulin spike so you have
a more level blood sugar level. Getting
your blood sugar to 180 or 200 is going
to cause problems in your body. It's
going to lead to insulin resistance over
time. It's going to lead to cancer over
time. Lower your blood sugar. Have it
more stable. Get your A1C down to five
or 4.9 or 4.8 ideally. I know it's it's
difficult. It's difficult in America
where we have [__] for food. Uh but
again, I'm giving you the best case
scenario and if you meet me 70% of the
way, you're still making improvements.
So to recap, if you are 35, 40, 45 or
older, consider being monitored, tested,
evaluated, and treated potentially by a
competent provider for hormone therapy
replacement.
And if you're a young guy and you're
sub-optimal, then those changes are
really all you should be focused on at
the time. If you're older and you are on
hormones, you should still focus on the
changes I just mentioned. And those are
just basics. Those are just basics that
we're all guilty of. Alcohol, poor
sleep, sugar, and caffeine. Those four
things will be life-changing for the
quality of your life. pick and choose
your battles, but in a perfect world,
those are the four that I would go with
when it comes to the top worst habits
that people have that they really don't
see as bad habits.